If anything can concisely summarize the
present predicament facing New Zealand,
it's this single number, 73,852.
In the 12 months leading up to August
2025, 73,852
Kiwis immigrated. In other words, 73,852
is the number of Kiwis that packed their
bags and booked one-way tickets out of
the isolated island nation to build a
new life somewhere else. Broken down,
that's 202 people a day, nearly enough
to fill an Air New Zealand A321
aircraft. More than doubling the number
of Kiwis lost in both World Wars, or
ranking as the country's ninth largest
if it were a city. This number by itself
is a major concern. Making the problem
only more glaring is that more than a
third of those leaving are aged 18 to 30
years old, making the problem only more
structural. Long-term immigration by New
Zealand citizens has been steadily
rising for more than a decade. From 2015
to 2025, the cumulative total is at
454,000,
a number larger than all New Zealand
cities aside from Auckland. 73,852
is not a fluke, but rather a sign of the
times. Now, there are plenty of theories
informing why Kiwis are leaving, but
simply consider where this diaspora is
headed and a clearer picture takes
shape. Australia. With the vast majority
of these departures headed across the
Tasmin Sea, it's the recently
established extremely close relationship
between these two countries that's
sitting at the center of this developing
demographic disaster. across the entire
English-speaking world, even within the
core five nations of the Anglophere, the
US, Canada, UK, Australia, and New
Zealand, all of which sharing British
heritage, democratic structures, and
close economic relationships, no two
nations are nearly as culturally,
politically, and economically aligned as
Australia and New Zealand. Culturally,
just as an unaccustomed outsider may
confuse an American and a Canadian
because they sound similar, they listen
to mostly the same music, they both
watch the same professional sports
leagues that span the two nations, an
outsider may do the same with a Kiwi and
an Aussie. They're both likely to care
about rugby, they're both probably proud
of their Pavlova desserts. They share a
lot of popular culture, and they too
sound similar to the untrained ear. But
culture only acts as the visible surface
level of the closeness between the two
countries. If a New Zealand citizen
wants to visit Australia, no problem.
All one needs is a passport. Again, not
so different from the US Canada
experience. But if that same Kiwi wants
to stay for a while and work, again, no
problem. They just need a passport.
Should they want to live in the country
for a while, well, that's fine, too.
Just a passport. Only until a Kiwi wants
to begin being considered for state
benefits does a visa come into question.
And should they eventually decide they
want to become a citizen, they simply
need to be present in the country for
four years and a full-time resident for
one. In fact, flipping between the two
and becoming a citizen is seen as such a
small deal in the scheme of things that
a note on the government website asks
those pursuing citizenship to make sure
that they aren't already by law an
Australian without knowing it. For
Aussies and Kiwis, it's easier to work
and move between the two than it is for
a Canadian and an American. And it's
easier to become a naturalized citizen
than it is for anyone moving between
countries in the EU. This unique
closeness carries over to business, too.
Whereas trade across the US Canada
border is paperwork intensive,
increasingly politicized, and subject to
tariffs, business between New Zealand
and Australia functions almost as if
there's no border at all. working
towards a fully integrated international
economic understanding called the single
economy market. Trade and business
relations between the two resemble what
you'd see across American states or the
UK without the historical baggage that
may inform how a Scott thinks of a Brit.
Whether it's relocating, naturalizing,
working, or doing business, there's
really no two large developed countries
outside Europe where the movement
between them is as seamless. All this is
relatively new. In the 1890s, these six
British colonies comprising present- day
Australia began the process of coming
together as a country. An Australian
national identity had begun to develop.
Concerns over defense had heightened and
frustrations over the economic
inefficiencies of not having a single
national market for foods and services
had become too much. At the first of a
series of conferences hammering out the
details, New Zealand sent delegates at
home. They began floating the idea of
joining this developing Commonwealth.
Ultimately though, they chose not to.
And while much is often made of the fact
that Australia's 1901 constitution
ultimately left room for New Zealand to
join, less is made of the fact that they
didn't want to. Their own independently
governed colony with a fruitful trade
relationship with Britain. New
Zealanders believe their culture to be
too different. Their policies towards
indigenous people to in congress with
Australia's and their economies not yet
potential allies but rather export
rivals. For much of the early 1900s, New
Zealand maintained its distance from
Australia and benefited from it. With
the aid of refrigerated shipping, a
temperate climate ideal for animal
husbandry, and a wildly prosperous trade
relationship with the ever
resource-hungry Britain, the New Zealand
economy, on the back of raw agricultural
exports, soared. By the 1950s, by GDP
per capita, New Zealand had become the
world's third most productive,
prosperous economy. But then came
the60s, and with it change in the form
of synthetic wool and Britain entering
the European economic community.
Suddenly, a one-trick pony economy had
to diversify. New Zealand built
factories. It explored exporting to
other markets like the US and Asia. It
expanded state services. And ultimately,
it faltered. In the age of global
liberalization of Reagan and Thatcher,
New Zealand underwent its own process of
difficult right sizing through
Rogeromics. By this point, in the 1980s,
Australia's economy had surpassed the
productivity of New Zealand's for good.
And with few other promising options,
New Zealand came to the table with their
neighbor to figure out a trade
relationship that would mirror those
taking shape in Europe. First came the
closer economic relations agreement in
1983. With tariffs and quantified
restrictions between the two countries
phased out, a new trading partnership
bloomed, growing by 500% over 20 years.
It was a watershed moment. The fruitful
agreement was taken further. In 1998,
the two agreed that products that passed
inspection and testing and became
legally available to consumers in one
country could now be sold in the other
without any questions asked. This was
then extended to the workforce. Anyone
who obtained lensure in most any field
in one country was able to perform the
same work in the other. The relationship
was further crystallized with the single
economic market agreement of 2009. This
has made it even easier for businesses
to work across the Tasmin Sea by setting
up TransT Tasmin regulatory bodies and
essentially turning the hard borders
between the two countries into something
closer resembling ever permeable dotted
lines. For both nations, coming together
in a time of real uncertainty in the
1980s has been a major success and
stabilizing factor. But recently for New
Zealand, it's begun to show some
difficult downsides.
What's killing New Zealand is that such
a permeable border between two nations
is allowing Australia's gravitational
pull to impact New Zealand's population.
There are two simple metrics that inform
the critical differences between the two
countries, population and GDP per
capita. At 27.2 million people,
Australia's about five times the size of
New Zealand. And in GDP per capita,
Australia's at 12th in the world with
$66,000,
while New Zealand lags behind at 25th
with $49,000.
These two Gulfs have real consequences
for New Zealand. Just take any Auckland
kid about to make a decision on where to
go to college, for example. Because the
two nations are now so closely tethered,
any graduating Kiwi has the opportunity
to cross the Tasmin and study in
Australia without a student visa while
paying the domestic rate for university
rather than the international fee. Of
course, it should be said the same
exists for an Aussie looking toward New
Zealand. But let's say a student from
either of these countries is looking for
a bigger campus with a larger range of
paths of study. In New Zealand, there
are six universities that boast a
student body over 20,000 with University
of Auckland far and away the largest
with 45,000 students. In just the
Australian state of Victoria, there are
seven such universities. In New South
Wales, another nine. And should this
student be a high achiever, it's four
Australian universities versus zero New
Zealand schools cracking the US News top
50 list. And it's not until number 10
before you find a New Zealand university
in the top regional universities across
the two countries. For a prospective
student, Australia just provides more
opportunities and for the high achiever,
more prestigious pathways. Furthering
the hypothetical, let's say this postcol
student is interested in getting into
investment banking. In Sydney, there's
the big international names. There's
Goldman Sachs. There's Morgan Stanley
right across the street. Right below it
is UBS and a few blocks down there's JP
Morgan. There are also offices of
Barkley, City Bank, and Bank of America.
In Auckland, there's barely any
investment banking. While City Bank does
technically have a presence with an
office here, banking of any sort in New
Zealand is dominated by A&Z, ASB, Bank
of New Zealand, and Westpak New Zealand,
three of which are subsidiaries of banks
in Australia, the fourth originally
founded in New South Wales. So should
someone want to get into investment
banking, their best bet would be to
attend university within the collection
of the group of eight, the region's most
selective universities, all of which
located in Australia, then head to
Sydney. For banking or anything finance
related, it just makes sense to base
operations out of Australia as the
infrastructure already exists, the
currency is more international, the
markets just bigger. While intuitive,
this in turn stunts any potential
development for New Zealand's financial
industry, as it just makes far more
sense to simply go to Australia and
quite potentially never come back. Now,
in New Zealand's culture, it may not be
the end of the world to be losing its
finance bros, but losing their tax
dollars and their subsequent local
spending cost the nation's economy.
This trend exists beyond the finance and
white collar hypotheticals, too. In
2021, this advertisement ran in the New
Zealand Herald, sponsored by the state
of Queensland. They were looking to pull
registered nurses across the ditch to
fill vacancies across a host of
facilities with the promise that the
state had a reasonable working
conditions, livable cities, and warm
weather. The timing was opportunistic as
New Zealand healthcare workers had gone
on protest just a month earlier
demanding better working conditions and
pay. Those who followed the
advertisement west reported back that
the jobs lived up to the promise. They
had fewer patients per nurse and they
got paid better. By March of 2024, of
the 38,000 nurses registered in
Australia that year, 10,000 hailed from
New Zealand. With such asymmetrical
opportunity in education and employment,
New Zealand is hemorrhaging able workers
in a classic case of brain drain. The
country is able to raise middle and
high-income workers, but is increasingly
unable to keep them, their skills, and
their dollars at home. Of course, with
such open borders and similar cultures,
people go both ways. Australians invest
their time and money in New Zealand,
too. But it looks different. On average,
if an Australian is planning to go to
New Zealand, it's either to visit, to
retire, or to check on their real estate
investment. All of which brings money
across the Tasmin, but money that does
less to grow the economy and money that
has a complicated impact on the nation's
direction. Tourism, for instance, is a
major part of the New Zealand economy.
It employs some 10% of the population,
at least indirectly. It accounts for
about 7.5% of the nation's GDP. And with
between a third and half of all tourists
hailing from Australia, the entire
industry relies on its neighbors to keep
it afloat. In a place like Queenstown
with beautiful waterways abudded by
dramatic snowcapped mountains, tourism
does an amazing job of commercializing
what would otherwise be some pretty
inhospitable landscapes. In this way,
tourism does a lot for a rather rugged
and rocky nation. The thing is, tourism
is a difficult industry to turn into a
career. One can work at one of the two
ski resorts near Queenstown, but it's
only a seasonal job from June to
October. It's a job that won't likely
require a degree, and one that will
count on young adventure oriented
employees, and thus will not pay well.
The same limitations will go for a raft
guide, a luxury hotel employee, a server
at the popular restaurant in the heart
of town. Employment will probably be
seasonal. Pay will be at the whims of
visitation trends well beyond their
control. Jobs will perpetually remain
entry level. Career advancement will be
limited, and benefits will be
non-existent. Australians will come
visit, spend their money, stimulate the
economy for the moment, but ultimately
perpetuate a system with fairly limited
long-term viability. The same goes with
Australians that make the move
permanent, those that retire there.
While they're moving in, stimulating the
real estate market, spending their
disposable funds at local businesses,
they're bringing little to the table
when it comes to growing the country's
economic output, benefiting its age
pyramid, and simply by buying into the
markets, only making the housing crisis
just a touch worse for the average Kiwi.
What's easy to lose sight of when
considering New Zealand and Australia is
that while they're both extremely
isolated island nations, one is far
smaller and more isolated than the
other. That informs some important push
factors. If Kiwis are pulled to
Australia, they're also pushed by the
fact that life is just generally more
expensive and less convenient. For a lot
of products, New Zealand status on the
very edge of global trade routes doesn't
matter too much. Take imported Twinnings
tea or Cadbury chocolate bars. They're
fairly similar priced in both Australia
and New Zealand. And when compared to
those available in the US, they're
actually cheaper. Global shipping has
figured products like this out. They're
shelf stable, small, easy to handle, and
thus cheap to move and cheap to buy. But
when there are blips in this system, New
Zealand's far more likely to lose out.
Take a fresher and more difficult
product, orange juice. In 2024, orange
juice prices started to rise at every
Kiwi's local Woolworths. Then the
cartons began to disappear entirely.
This was on account of a faraway cyclone
in Brazil that set the global orange
juice supply behind on account of a lack
of orange juice. In Australia though,
the shortage was minimized by the fact
that there's a fairly strong orange
industry domestically, a benefit of the
country spanning three climate zones
from aid to tropical. Even in things
that New Zealand is well equipped to
produce, goods are expensive. Take beef.
If a Kiwi is going to buy ground beef,
it's going to be largely at the global
going rate as beef is a major export for
the country. That means when beef is in
tight demand and the market rate rises
globally, for Kiwis to entice New
Zealand producers to sell locally, they
have to roughly match the rate. Buying
beef at the international rate though is
expensive for the average New Zealander
because their purchasing power is
hamstrung by a less and less productive
economy. By monthly cost of living,
which considers everything from rent to
grocery bills, New Zealand's in the
world's top 25 most expensive, while by
purchasing power parody, New Zealand's
at 36th near countries where the price
of living is much lower. No matter how
much a Kiwi may love their home country,
this massive disparity between
purchasing power and price of living is
crippling. It's simply a massively
difficult place to make ends meet. While
Australia is even more expensive on a
cost of living basis, its PPP ranking is
a whole 40 spots higher. Rent will be
higher, but so will wages and earning
potential. Increasingly, as more and
more Australian companies come to
establish important holdings and provide
important services in New Zealand,
whether it's the banks, the grocery
stores like Woolworths and Kohl's, the
gas stations like Ample, or the food
distributor Goodman Fielder. And as more
New Zealanders look to access
opportunity in the wider world through
moving to Australia, the relationship
between the two feels less and less
equal. It feels not like the interaction
between two sovereign self-interested
countries and more so the interaction of
a far-flung down at its luck state and
the prosperous nation within which it
resides. On balance, the softening of
borders between Australia and New
Zealand seems to benefit the former far
more than the latter. Australia receives
access to new markets, a host of hungry
young professionals, and a beautiful and
convenient destination to travel. New
Zealand, in turn, has an important
economic ally, a market to send its
goods, and an army of tourists to pump
at least some money into the country.
It's an uneven agreement, and one that's
costing New Zealand far more than it's
costing Australia, is an imbalance
informed by size and geography beyond
the control of either. But it's
ultimately an imbalanced deal that
likely isn't going anywhere soon. Ask a
Kiwi and they're not likely to harbor
any bitterness towards Australia and
this imbalance of benefits. Ask a New
Zealand politician and you'll get much
the same. There's little to no animosity
toward the nation taking some of its
best and brightest. Immigration is a
real problem, but immigration is a
consequence of a deal that New Zealand
relies on. Remove Australia from the
equation and New Zealand is only in more
trouble, more isolated, and left with
fewer prospects. A colonial enterprise
from the beginning, New Zealand is a
global nation with global ambitions. And
to act on such ambitions as the most
isolated major nation in the world comes
with real trade-offs.
Trade-offs and difficult decisions,
though, should not be defining your
shaving routine. Far too long in my own
life, I've had to weigh the decision
between growing out some stubble or
inevitably irritating my skin with any
and every razor that just seemed to maul
my face and always make the routine an
unpleasant one. But all that changed
when I gave Hensen Shaving, the sponsor
of this video, a try. For years, I've
used razors that could give me a fine
enough, close, clean looking shave. But
not until I gave Hensen a shot did they
actually feel good. That's because Henen
has been designing around the feel and
experience of the shave as well as the
look. And they've come up with the
Hensen razor. These are made in an
aerospace machine shop. They're all
aluminum, and everything from the angle
of the razor blade to its blade support
was designed to turn shaving from an
irritating hassle into just another part
of your morning routine. In a space
where marketing gimmicks, subscription
models, and a whole lot of plastic waste
has become the norm, Henson has quietly
innovated and my mornings are better
because of it. If you'd like to give
their product a shot and support a
company that's supporting us, head to
hensenshaving.com/wendover
and enter Wendover at checkout to get
100 free blades with your purchase. It's
a switch that I really think you're
going to appreciate making.